<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % commondata SYSTEM "../entities/common.ent" > %commondata;
]>
<chapter id="basics">
<title>The basics</title>

<para>This chapter contains a brief overview of the build process as well as containing instructions on how to boot the various binary image types.</para>

<section>
<title>What is a live system?</title>

<para>A live system usually means an OS booted on a computer from a removable support (as CD-ROM, USB stick, or network), ready to use without any installation on the usual drive(s), with an auto-configuration done at runtime (see <xref linkend="terms"/>).</para>

<para>With Debian Live, it's a Debian GNU/Linux OS, built for one of the supported architectures (currently amd64, i386, powerpc and sparc). It is made from following parts:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Linux kernel</term>
<listitem><para>The Linux image, usually named <filename>vmlinuz*</filename>.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Initial RAM disk image (initrd)</term>
<listitem><para>RAM disk setup for the Linux boot, containing modules possibly needed to mount the filesystem's image and some scripts to do it.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>System image</term>
<listitem><para>The O.S. image. Debian Live uses a SquashFS image, a compressed filesystem, to minimize its size. Note that it's read-only, so during boot, the Debian Live system will uses RAM disk and 'union' mechanism to be able to write files on the system, but all modifications will be lost when shutdown, until using optional persistence partition(s) (see <xref linkend="persistence"/>).</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Bootloader</term>
<listitem><para>A small piece of code, crafted to boot up from the chosen media, possibly proposing a prompt or menu to let select options/configuration, then loading the Linux kernel and its initrd to let it run with associated filesystem image. Different solutions can be proposed depending of the target media and format of filesystem containing the previous components: Isolinux to boot from a CD or DVD in ISO9660 format, syslinux for HDD or USB drive boot from a VFAT partition, GRUB for ext2/3 partition, pxelinux for PXE netboot...</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>The Debian Live tools will build the system image from your specifications, setup a Linux kernel and its initrd, a bootloader to run them, all in one media-dependant format(ISO9660 image, disk image, ...).</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>First steps: building an ISO image</title>

<para>The following sequence of helper commands, provided by &live-helper;, will create a basic ISO image containing just the Debian standard system without X.org. It is suitable for burning to CD or DVD media.</para>
<para>First, we run the <filename>lh_config</filename> helper command which will create a <filename>"config/"</filename> hierarchy in the current directory for use by other helper commands:</para>
<screen>$ lh_config</screen>
<para>By passing no parameters to <filename>lh_config</filename>, we indicated that we wish to use the defaults, which will create an image of type binary (see <xref linkend="lh_config"/>).</para>
<para>Now that we have a <filename>"config/"</filename> hierarchy, we may build the image with <filename>lh_build</filename> helper command:</para>
<screen># lh_build</screen>
<para>This process can take a while, depending on the speed of your network connection (see <xref linkend="lh_build"/>).</para>

<section>
<title>Testing an ISO image with Qemu</title>

<para>Testing an ISO is simple:</para>
<screen>
# apt-get install qemu
$ qemu -cdrom binary.iso
</screen>
</section>

<section>
<title>Burning an ISO image to physical medium</title>

<para>Burning an ISO image is easy:</para>
<screen>
# apt-get install wodim
$ wodim binary.iso
</screen>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Building an USB/HDD image</title>

<para>The following sequence of helper commands will create a basic USB/HDD image containing just the Debian standard system without X.org. It is suitable for booting from USB sticks, USB hard drives, and various other portable storage devices.</para>
<para>Note if you created an iso image with the previous example, you will need to clean up your working directory with the <filename>lh_clean</filename> helper command (see <xref linkend="lh_clean"/>):</para>
<screen>$ lh_clean --binary</screen>
<para>Run the <filename>lh_config</filename> helper command with the parameters to configure the <filename>"config/"</filename> hierarchy to create a USD/HDD image type:</para>
<screen>$ lh_config -b usb-hdd</screen>
<para>Now build the image with <filename>lh_build</filename> helper command:</para>
<screen># lh_build</screen>

<section>
<title>Copying USB/HDD image to a USB stick</title>

<para>The generated binary image contains a <acronym>VFAT</acronym> partition and the <command>syslinux</command> bootloader, ready to be directly written on an USB stick. Plug in an USB stick with a size larger than <filename>binary.img</filename>'s one, and type:
<screen>$ dd if=binary.img of=${USBSTICK}</screen>
where <replaceable>${USBSTICK}</replaceable> is the device file of your key, like <filename>/dev/sda</filename> (not a partition like <filename>/dev/sda1</filename>!); you can find the right device name by looking in <command>dmesg</command>'s output after plugging the stick, for example).</para>
<important>This will definitely overwrite any previous contents on youro stick!</important>
</section>

<section>
<title>Testing a USB/HDD image with Qemu</title>
<screen>
# apt-get install qemu
$ qemu -hda binary.img
</screen>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Building a netboot image</title>

<para>The following sequence of helper commands will create a basic netboot image containing the Debian standard system without X.org. It is suitable for booting over the network.</para>
<para>Note if you performed any previous examples, you will need to clean up your working directory with the <filename>lh_clean</filename> helper command:</para>
<screen>$ lh_clean --binary</screen>
<para>Run the <filename>lh_config</filename> helper command with the parameters to configure the <filename>"config/"</filename> hierarchy to create our netboot image:</para>
<screen>$ lh_config -b net --net-root-path "/srv/debian-live" --net-root-server "192.168.0.1"</screen>
<para>In contrast with the ISO and USB hdd images, netbooting does not support serving a filesystem image with the client so the files must be served via NFS. The <replaceable>net-root-path</replaceable> and <replaceable>net-root-server</replaceable> options specify the location and server respectfully of the NFS server where the filesytem image will be located at boot-time.</para>
<para>Now build the image with <filename>lh_build</filename> helper command:</para>
<screen># lh_build</screen>
<para>In a network boot, the client runs a small piece of software, usually on the <acronym>EEPROM</acronym> of the Ethernet card, which sends a <abbrev>DHCP</abbrev> request  to get an <abbrev>IP</abbrev> address and also information about what to do next; such as getting (through <abbrev>TFTP</abbrev> protocol) a higher level boot software like <application>Grub</application> or <application>PXLINUX</application>, or directly to an operating system like <application>Linux</application>.</para>
<para>For example, you can extract the generated <filename>binary-net.tar.gz</filename> archive in the <filename>/srv/debian-live</filename> directory; you'll get the filesystem image in <filename>live/filesystem.squashfs</filename>, the kernel, initrd and PXE Linux bootloader in <filename>tftpboot/debian-live/i386</filename>.</para>
<para>We must now configure three services on the server:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>DHCP server</term>
<listitem>
<para>We must configure our network's DHCP server to be sure to give a <abbrev>IP</abbrev> address to the computer netbooting, and to advertise the location of the PXE bootloader.</para>
<para>Here is an example for inspiration, written for the ISC DHCP server (package <literal>dhcp3-server</literal>) in the <filename>/etc/dhcp3/dhcpd.conf</filename> configuration file :</para>
<screen>
# Options DHCP spécifiques à Pxelinux:
option space pxelinux;
option pxelinux.magic      code 208 = string;
option pxelinux.configfile code 209 = text;
option pxelinux.pathprefix code 210 = text;
option pxelinux.reboottime code 211 = unsigned integer 32;


subnet 192.168.1.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 {   # 192.168.1.0/24

  # IP addresses available for guests
  range 192.168.1.100 192.168.1.149;

  # allow booting from the net
  allow bootp;

  # for net booting, server where the first file to be loaded (by TFTP
  # protocol) ("filename" following definition) lies : so the TFTP
  # server's name.
  next-server myserver;

  # net boot configuration for guests with a PXE client :
  if substring (option vendor-class-identifier, 0, 9) = "PXEClient" {
    # Note : all files for PXE are relatives to the TFTP server's root
    # path, as usually defined in /etc/inetd.conf.

    # PXE boot loader (first program to be loaded, by TFTP)
    filename "pxelinux.0";

    # describe some specific pxelinux's options through DHCP options :
    site-option-space "pxelinux";
    option pxelinux.magic f1:00:74:7e;
    if exists dhcp-parameter-request-list {
      # Always send the PXELINUX options (specified in hexadecimal)
      option dhcp-parameter-request-list = concat(option dhcp-parameter-request-list,d0,d1,d2,d3);
    }

    # For a PXE boot menu, different versions are available : simple
    # text, text with curses, graphic (VESA)
    #option pxelinux.configfile "pxelinux/config_simple";
    #option pxelinux.configfile "pxelinux/config_curses";
    option pxelinux.configfile "pxelinux/config_vesa";

    # automatically reboot after 10 minutes of no activity
    option pxelinux.reboottime 600;
  }
}
</screen>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>TFTPd server</term>
<listitem>
<para>This serves the kernel and initial ramdisk to the system at run-time.</para>
<para>You should install the <command>tftpd-hpa</command> package. It can serve all files contained inside a root directory, usually <filename>/var/lib/tftpboot/</filename>, as defined with its <option>-s</option> option. To let it serves files inside <filename>/srv/debian-live/tftpboot</filename>, modify its start definition in <filename>/etc/inetd.conf</filename> with:
<screen>tftp           dgram   udp     wait    root  /usr/sbin/in.tftpd /usr/sbin/in.tftpd -s /srv/debian-live/tftpboot -r blksize -v -v</screen>
and reload the super server with <command>/etc/init.d/openbsd-inetd reload</command>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>NFS server</term>
<listitem>
<para>Once the guest computer will have downloaded and booted a Linux kernel and its initrd, it will try to mount the Live filesystem image through a NFS server.</para>
<para>You should install the <command>nfs-kernel-server</command> server package -- <command>nfs-user-server</command> does not function correctly with netboot.</para>
<para>Then, declare that the directory of the filesystem image is available through NFS, by writing in <filename>/etc/exports</filename> :</para>
<screen>/srv/debian-live *(ro,async,subtree_check,no_root_squash)</screen>
<para>and let the NFS server knowing it typing following command :</para>
<screen># exportfs -rv</screen>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>Setting all these services is quite error prone, you'll need some patience to let all of them working together.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title> Netboot testing HowTo </title>


<para>Netboot images creation is made easy with live-helper magic, but testing the images on physical machines can be really time consuming.
To make our life easier, we can use virtualization. There are two solutions:
</para>


<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>VMWare Player</term>
<listitem>
<para> Install VMWare Player ("free as in beer" edition)</para>
<para> Create a PXETester directory, and create a text file called pxe.vwx inside</para>
<para> Paste this text inside: </para>
<screen>
#!/usr/bin/vmware
config.version = "8"
virtualHW.version = "4"
memsize = "512"
MemAllowAutoScaleDown = "FALSE"

ide0:0.present = "FALSE"
ide1:0.present = "FALSE"
floppy0.present = "FALSE"
sound.present = "FALSE"
tools.remindInstall = "FALSE"

ethernet0.present = "TRUE"
ethernet0.addressType = "generated"

displayName = "Test Boot PXE"
guestOS = "other"

ethernet0.generatedAddress = "00:0c:29:8d:71:3b"
uuid.location = "56 4d 83 72 5c c4 de 3f-ae 9e 07 91 1d 8d 71 3b"
uuid.bios = "56 4d 83 72 5c c4 de 3f-ae 9e 07 91 1d 8d 71 3b"
ethernet0.generatedAddressOffset = "0"
</screen>
<para>You can play with this configuration file (i.e. change memory limit to 256)</para>
<para>Double click on this file (or run VMWare player and selecet this file).</para>
<para>When running just press space if that strange question comes up... </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>


<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>Qemu</term>
<listitem>
<para>Install qemu, bridge-utils, sudo.</para>
<para>Edit <filename>/etc/qemu-ifup</filename>:</para>
<screen>
#!/bin/sh
sudo -p "Password for $0:" /sbin/ifconfig $1 172.20.0.1
echo "Executing /etc/qemu-ifup"
echo "Bringing up $1 for bridged mode..."
sudo /sbin/ifconfig $1 0.0.0.0 promisc up
echo "Adding $1 to br0..."
sudo /usr/sbin/brctl addif br0 $1
sleep 2
</screen>
<para>Get, or build a grub-floppy-netboot (in the svn).</para>
<para>Launch qemu with "-net nic,vlan=0 -net tap,vlan=0,ifname=tun0" </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</section>
</chapter>
