<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % commondata SYSTEM "../entities/common.ent" > %commondata;
]>
<chapter id="bugs">
<title>Reporting bugs</title>

<para>Debian Live is far from being perfect, but we want to make it as close as possible to perfect - with your help. Do not hesitate to report a bug: it is better to fill a report twice than never. However, this chapter includes recommendations how to file good bug reports.</para>

<para>For the impatient:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>
  Always check first the image status updates on <ulink url="http://debian-live.alioth.debian.org/">our homepage</ulink> for known issues.
  </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
 <para>
  Always try to reproduce the bug with the <emphasis>most recent version of &live-helper; and &live-initramfs;</emphasis> before submitting a bug report.
 </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
 <para>
  Try to give <emphasis>as specific information as possible</emphasis> about the bug. This includes (at least) the version of &live-helper; and &live-initramfs; used and the distribution of the live system you are building.
 </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<section id="known-issues">
<title>Known issues</title>
<para>Due to the nature of Debian testing and Debian unstable branches being a moving target, building a live system may not always be possible.</para>
<para>If this is a problem, do not build a system based on testing or unstable, but go with stable. live-helper does always default to the current stable release.</para>
<para>Currently known issues are listed under the section 'Image status' on <ulink url="http://debian-live.alioth.debian.org/">our homepage</ulink>.</para>
<para>It is out of the scope of this manual to train you in correctly identifying and fixing problems in packages of the development branches, however, there are two things you can always try: When not succeeding to build testing, try if unstable works. If unstable does not work either, revert to testing and pinning the newer version of the failing package from unstable.</para>
</section>

<section id="rebuild-from-scratch">
<title>Rebuild from scratch</title>
<para>To ensure that a particular bug is not caused by an unclean built system, please always rebuild the whole live system from scratch to see if the bug is reproducible.</para>
</section>

<section id="up-to-date">
<title>Use up-to-date packages</title>
<para>This means</para>

<para>Using outdated packages can cause significant problems when trying to reproduce (and ultimately fix) your problem. If a relevant package is not available in Debian anymore, please recognize that the resources of the Debian kernel team are limited and will be unlikely to be able to fix the problem.</para>
</section>


<section id="collect-information">
<title>Collect information</title>

<para>Please provide enough information with your report. At a minimum, it should contain the exact version of &live-helper; version where the bug is encountered, and steps to reproduce it. Please use common sense and include other relevant information if you think that it might help in solving the problem.</para>

<para>To make the most out of your bug report, we require at least the following
information:</para>

<itemizedlist>
 <listitem><para>Architecture of the host system</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Version of &live-helper; on the host system</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Version of &live-initramfs; on the live system</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Version of <filename>debootstrap</filename> and/or <filename>cdebootstrap</filename> on the host system</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Architecture of the live system</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Distribution of the live system</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Version of the kernel on the live system</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
 You can generate a log of the build process by using the <filename>tee</filename> command:
</para>

<screen>
 # lh_build 2>&amp;1 | tee buildlog.txt
</screen>

<para>Additionally, to rule out other errors, it is always a good idea to tar up
your config directory and upload it somewhere (do *not* send it as an attachment
to the mailinglist), so that we can try to reproduce the errors you
encountered.</para>

<para>Remember to send in any logs that were produced with English locale
settings, e.g. run your live-helper commands with a leading
<code>LC_ALL=C</code> or <code>LC_ALL=en_US</code>.</para>


</section>

<section id="correct-package">
<title>Use the correct package to report the bug against</title>

<para>Where does the bug appear?</para>

<para>
<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>At build time whilst bootstrapping</term>

<listitem><para>
<para>&live-helper; first bootstraps a basic Debian system with <command>debootstrap</command> or <command>cdebootstrap</command>. Depending on the bootstrapping tool used and the Debian distribution it is bootstrapping, it may fail. If a bug appears here, check if the error is related to a specific Debian package (most likely), or if it is related to cdebootstrap itself.</para>

<para>In both cases, this is not a bug in Debian Live, but rather in Debian itself which we can not fix this directly. Please report such a bug against <command>debootstrap</command>, <command>cdebootstrap</command> or the failing package.</para>
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>At build time whilst installing packages</term>

<listitem><para>&live-helper; installs additional packages from the Debian archive and depending on the Debian distribution used and the daily archive state, it can fail. If a bug appears here, check if the error is also reproducible on a normal system.</para>

<para>If this is the case, this is not a bug in Debian Live, but rather in Debian - please report it against the failing package. Running <filename>debootstrap</filename> seperately from the Live system build or running <filename>lh_bootstrap</filename> with <command>--debug</command> will give you more information.</para>

<para>Also, if you are using a local mirror and/or any of sort of proxy and you are experiencing a problem, please always reproduce it first by bootstrapping from an official mirror.</para>

</listitem>

</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>At boot-time</term>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   If your image does not boot, please report it to the mailing list together with the information requested in <xref linkend="collect-information"/>. Do not forget to mention, how/when the image failed, in Qemu, VMWare or real hardware. If you are using a virtualization technology of any kind, please always run it on real hardware before reporting a bug. Providing a screenshot of the failure is also very helpful.
  </para>
 </listitem>
</varlistentry> 

<varlistentry><term>At run-time</term>

<listitem><para>If a package was successfully installed, but fails while actually running the Live system, this is probably a bug in Debian Live. However, </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</para>

</section>

<section id="research">
<title>Do the research</title>
<para>Before filing the bug, please search the web for the particular error message or symptom you are getting. As it is highly unlikely that you are the only person experiencing a particular problem, there is always a chance that it has been discussed elsewhere, and a possible solution, patch, or workaround has been proposed.</para>

<para>You should pay particular attention to the Debian Live mailing list, as well as the homepage, as these are likely to contain the most up-to-date information. If such information exists, always include the references to it in your bug report.</para>

<para>In addition, you should check the <ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/pkgreport.cgi?src=live-helper">current bug list for &live-helper;</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/pkgreport.cgi?src=live-initramfs">current bug list for live-initramfs</ulink> to see whether something similar has been reported already.</para>
</section>

<section id="where">
<title>Where to report bugs</title>

<para>The Debian Live project keeps track of all bugs in the Debian Bug Tracking System (BTS). For information on how to use the system, please see <ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org">http://bugs.debian.org</ulink>. You can also submit the bugs by using the <command>reportbug</command> command from the package with the same name.</para>

<para>In general, you should report build time errors against the <ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/pkgreport.cgi?src=live-helper">live-helper</ulink> package and run time errors against <ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/pkgreport.cgi?src=live-initramfs">live-initramfs</ulink>. If you are unsure of which package is appropriate or need more help before submitting a bug report, please send a message to the mailing list and we will help you to figure it out.</para>

<para>Please note that bugs found in distributions derived from Debian (such as Ubuntu, Knoppix, Xandros, etc.) should <emphasis>not</emphasis> be reported to the Debian BTS unless they can be also reproduced on a Debian system using official Debian packages.</para>

</section>

</chapter>
