<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % commondata SYSTEM "../../ent/common.ent" > %commondata;
]>
<sect1 id="packages">
<title>Customising package installation</title>

<para>
 This chapter discusses the customisation of package installation. This involves:
</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>Selecting additional packages to be installed</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Installing modified packages</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<sect2 id="package-sources">
<title>Package sources</title>
<para>
 FIXME
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="package-installation">
<title>Package installation</title>
<para>
 You can elect to use either <computeroutput>apt</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>aptitude</computeroutput> when installing packages. Which utility is used is governed by the <computeroutput>LH_APT</computeroutput> variable in <filename>config/chroot</filename> or by the <computeroutput>--apt</computeroutput> argument to <filename>lh_config</filename>:
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><computeroutput>apt</computeroutput></term>
<listitem>
<para>
 Specifying a missing package causes package installation to fail, which may not be the desired behaviour.
</para>
<para>
 This is the default setting for building images for Lenny or later.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><computeroutput>aptitude</computeroutput></term>
<listitem>
<para>
 Specifying a missing package causes package installation to succeed, which may not be the desired behaviour.
</para>
<para>
 This is the default setting for building images for Etch.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Installing additional packages</title>

<para>
 &live-helper; has a number of mechanisms for indicating that additional packages should be installed, including:
</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>The <computeroutput>LH_PACKAGES</computeroutput> variable</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Package lists</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Local packages (<filename>chroot_local-packages/</filename>)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Tasks</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<sect3 id="lh-packages">
<title>The <computeroutput>LH_PACKAGES</computeroutput> variable</title>
<para>
 To install additional packages, simply add them to the <computeroutput>LH_PACKAGES</computeroutput> variable in <filename>config/chroot</filename>. For example:
</para>

<screen>
LH_PACKAGES="package1 package2 package3 ... "
</screen>

<para>
 You can also specify an initial values on the command line:
</para>

<screen>
$ lh_config --packages "package1 package2 package3"
</screen>

<para>The behaviour of &live-helper; when specifying a package that does not exist is determined by your choice of APT utility. See <xref linkend="package-installation"/> for more details.</para>

<para>
 If you need to specify a large number of packages to be installed or you need flexibility regarding which packages to install, you should probably be using package lists. See <xref linkend="package-lists"/> for more information.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="package-lists">
<title>Package lists</title>
<para>
 Package lists are a powerful way of expressing which packages should be installed. &live-helper; ships with a number of predefined package lists which provide sensible default package selections for the GNOME and KDE desktop environments, as well as standard systems.
</para>

<para>To specify a package list, add the name of the list to the <computeroutput>LH_PACKAGES_LISTS</computeroutput> variable in <filename>config/chroot</filename>. For example:</para>

<screen>
LH_PACKAGES_LISTS="gnome"
</screen>

<para>Packages lists that a distributed with &live-helper; reside in view in the <computeroutput>/usr/share/live-helper/lists</computeroutput> directory.</para>

<sect4>
<title>Local packages lists</title>
<para>
 You may supplement the supplied lists using local package lists stored in <computeroutput>config/chroot_local-packageslists</computeroutput>.
</para>
<para>
 Package lists that exist in this directory always override package lists distributed with &live-helper;. This can cause undesired effects when..
</para>

</sect4>

<sect4>
<title>Extending a provided package list using includes</title>
<para>FIXME.</para>

<screen>
#include &lt;gnome&gt;
iceweasel
</screen>

<para>
 The package lists that are included with &live-helper; make extensive use of includes. They are available to view in the <computeroutput>/usr/share/live-helper/lists</computeroutput> directory.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4>
<title>Using conditionals inside packages lists</title>
<para>FIXME</para>

<screen>
#if ARCHITECTURE amd64
ia32-libs
#endif
</screen>

<para>or if <computeroutput>LH_ARCHITECTURE</computeroutput> is set to <computeroutput>i386</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>amd64</computeroutput>:</para>

<screen>
#if ARCHITECTURE i386 amd64
memtest86+
#endif
</screen>

<para>or if <computeroutput>LH_SECTIONS</computeroutput> contains either <computeroutput>contrib</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>non-free</computeroutput>:</para>

<screen>
#if SECTIONS contrib non-free
vrms
#endif
</screen>

<para>A conditional may surround an <computeroutput>#include</computeroutput> directive:</para>

<screen>
#if ARCHITECTURE amd64
#include &lt;gnome-full&gt;
#endif
</screen>

<para>
 Any &live-helper; configuration variable that begins with <computeroutput>LH_</computeroutput> can be tested in this way.
</para>
<para>
 The nesting of conditionals is not supported.
</para>

</sect4>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="tasks">
<title>Tasks</title>
<para>FIXME</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="custom-packages">
<title>Installing modified or third-party packages</title>

<para>Whilst it is against the philosophy of Debian Live, it may sometimes be necessary to build a Live system with modified versions of packages that are in the Debian repository. This may be to modify or support additional features, languages and branding, or even to remove elements of existing packages that are undesirable. Similarly, "third-party" packages may be used to add bespoke and/or proprietary functionality.</para>

<para>This section does not cover advice regarding building or maintaining modified packages. Joachim Breitner's <ulink url="http://www.joachim-breitner.de/blog/archives/282-How-to-fork-privately.html">'How to fork privately'</ulink> may be of interest, however. The creation of bespoke packages is covered in the <ulink url="http://www.debian.org/doc/maint-guide/">Debian New Maintainers' Guide</ulink> and elsewhere.</para>

<para>There are two ways of installing modified custom packages:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><filename>chroot_local-packages</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Using a custom APT repository</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>The <filename>chroot_local-packages</filename> is simpler to achieve and useful for "one-off" customisations but has a number of drawbacks, whilst using a custom APT repository is more time-consuming to setup.</para>

<sect3 id="local-packages">
<title>Using <filename>chroot_local-packages</filename> to install custom packages</title>
<para>To install a custom package, simply copy it to the <computeroutput>config/chroot_local-packages</computeroutput> directory. Packages that are inside this directory will be automatically installed into the live system during build - you do not need to specify them elsewhere.</para>

<para>Packages <emphasis>must</emphasis> be named in the prescribed way. One simple way to is to use <computeroutput>dpkg-name</computeroutput>. FIXME</para>

<para>Using <filename>chroot_local-packages</filename> for installation of custom packages has two disadvantages:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>It is not possible to use secure APT</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>You must install all appropriate packages in the <computeroutput>config/chroot_local-packages</computeroutput> directory</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Does not lend itself to storing Debian Live configurations in revision control</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="custom-apt-repo">
<title>Using an APT repository to install custom packages</title>
<para>
 FIXME
</para>
<para>
 Unlike You must ensure that you specify the package elsewhere, see (FIXME)
</para>
<para>
 Whilst it may seem unnecessary effort to create an APT repository to install custom packages, the infrastructure can be easily re-used at a later date to offer updates of the modified package.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="custom-packages-apt">
<title>Custom packages and APT</title>
<para>
 &live-helper; uses APT to install all packages into the live system so will therefore inherit behaviours from this program. One relevant example is that (assuming a default configuration) given a package is available in two different repositories, APT will elect to install the package with a higher version number over one with the lower.
</para>

<para>
 Because of this. you may wish to increment the version number in your custom packages' <computeroutput>debian/changelog</computeroutput> files to ensure that your modified version is installed over one in the official Debian repositories. This may also be achieved by altering the live system's APT pinning preferences - see <xref linkend="apt-preferences"/> for more information.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="apt-preferences">
<title>Altering APT preferences during Live system</title>
<para>
 FIXME
</para>
<para>
 Whilst it may seem unnecessary effort to create an APT repository to install custom packages, the infrastructure can be easily re-used at a later date to offer updates of the modified package.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>
