<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % commondata SYSTEM "common.ent">
]>
<chapter id="common-tasks">
  <title>Common tasks</title>
  <section id="debian-installer">
    <title>The Debian Installer</title>
    <para> Although Debian Live is mostly concerned with avoiding permanent
installation, integrating some form of installer to your image is
possible. There are number of different "types" of installation, varying in
what and how to install the image. </para>
    <note>
      <title> The "Debian Installer" </title>
      <para> Please note the careful use of capital letters when referring to the "Debian
Installer" in this section - when used like this we refer explicitly to the
official installer for the Debian system, not anything else. It is often
seen abbreviated to "d-i". </para>
    </note>
    <para> The three main types of installer are: </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term> "Normal" Debian Installer </term>
        <listitem>
          <para> This is a normal Debian Live image with a seperate kernel and initrd which
(when selected from the appropriate bootloader) launches into a standard
Debian Installer instance, just as if you had downloaded a CD image of
Debian and booted it. </para>
          <para> This means that Debian is installed by fetching and installing
<command>.deb</command> packages using <filename>debootstrap</filename> or
<filename>cdebootstrap</filename>, from the local media or some network-base
network, resulting in a standard Debian system being installed to the hard
disk. </para>
          <para> This whole process can be preseeded and customised in a number of ways; see
the relevant "DebianInstaller" wiki page and installation guide for
more. This is operational now withing &live-helper;. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term> "Live" Debian Installer </term>
        <listitem>
          <para> This is a Debian Live image with a seperate kernel and initrd which (when
selected from the appropriate bootloader) launches into an instance of the
Debian Installer. </para>
          <para> Installation will proceed in an identical fashion to the "Normal"
installation described above, but at the actual package installation stage,
instead of using <filename>debootstrap</filename> to fetch and install
packages, the "live" filesystem image is copied to the target. After this
stage, the Debian Installer continues as normal, installing and configuring
items such as bootloaders and local users, etc. </para>
          <para> This is working now. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term> "Ubuntu"-style installer </term>
        <listitem>
          <para> This is where you boot into a graphical Debian Live system and run a
wizard-based program which installs and configures the live system, all the
time remaining inside the live graphical environment. </para>
          <para> This is currently NOT possible with Debian Live. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para> By default, no installer will be included in the Debian Live image. You can
enable it by using <filename>lh_config</filename> : <screen> $ lh_config --help ... [--debian-installer enabled|cdrom|netinst|netboot|businesscard|live|disabled] [--debian-installer-distribution CODENAME|daily] [--debian-installer-preseedfile FILE|URL] ... </screen> </para>
    <para> The values "Normal", "Live" and "Ubuntu" are not valid values for <term>LH_BINARY_DEBIAN_INSTALLER</term>. Refer to the output of <filename>lh_config</filename> cited above to
choose the appropriate values. </para>
  </section>
  <section id="wifi-connection">
    <title>WiFi Connection</title>
    <para> Depending on the Debian Live image you are using and the given tools
configured with your Debian Live image you may need to only attach to an
available access point. If you encounter difficulty a good place to start is
at the Debian Wiki entry for <ulink
url="http://wiki.debian.org/WiFi">WiFi</ulink>. </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
